Guide to the Rand School Archives Collection on Upton Sinclair TAM.425
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rand School Archives Collection on Upton Sinclair
1911-1964
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968
Rand School of Social Science
TAM.425
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
Upton Sinclair (September 20, 1878 - November 25, 1968) was a socialist and the author of The Jungle (1906), an expose of dangerous and unsanitary working conditions in the Chicago stockyards, who, in 1934, ran for governor of California on the Democratic Party ticket, basing his campaign around the slogan "End Poverty in California" (EPIC). The collection includes correspondence and manuscripts by Sinclair, bibliographies of his writings, as well as critical essays relating to his life and work.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1963.024.
Arrangement
The papers are organized into one alphabetically arranged series.
Historical/Biographical Note
Upton Sinclair (September 20, 1878 - November 25, 1968) was a socialist and author of books such as Manassas (1904) and The Jungle (1906), the latter becoming a world famous expose of dangerous and unsanitary working conditions in the Chicago stockyards, and which helped bring about the passage, later that year, of two federal laws, the Pure Food and Drug Act, and the Meat Inspection Act. In 1934, he ran for governor of California on the Democratic Party ticket, basing his campaign around the slogan "End Poverty in California" (EPIC).
Custodial History
The materials in this collection were assembled by the library of the Rand School of Social Science (later the Tamiment Institute and Library). In 1963, members of the People's Education Camp Society, Inc. transferred the collection to the Tamiment Library at New York University in 1963. The accession number associated with this gift is 1963.024
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Intercollegiate Socialist Society Records (Tamiment 048)
Daniel Bell Research Files on U.S. Communism, Socialism, and the Labor Movement (Tamiment 080)
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes correspondence and manuscripts by Sinclair, bibliographies of his writings, as well as critical essays relating to his life and work, including "Hercules Cleaning the Augean Stables with a Toothbrush," by Karl Radek, 1934, commenting on Sinclair's recent nomination as the Democratic candidate for the Governor of California.
Authors, American.; Elections |z California |y 1934.; Socialists -- United States.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Radek, Karl, 1885-1939.
- Papers, 1911-1964, undated; Series I.; 0.25 Linear Feet 1 box (Box 1)
  - Allat, Henry: Letter Requesting Copies of Sinclair/Related Manuscripts, Apr 20, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Dramatic World of Upton Sinclair: A Survey of the Published and Unpublished Plays (21 pp.) / Frederic Litto, Indiana University, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - In Memoriam (4 pp.) by Upton Sinclair [For his second wife, Mary Craig Kimbrough Sinclair (1883-1961)] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters by Sinclair, 1911, 1946-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Radek, Karl: Hercules Cleaning the Augean Stables with a Toothbrush (7 pp.; on Sinclair's California Gubernatorial nomination and campaign), [1934] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Spokesman's Secretary: Being the Letters of Mame to Mom: Letter I In Which I Join the Higher-ups / Upton Sinclair (29 pp.; 23" galley folded in half), Apr 14, 2926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tamiment Institute Library Bulletin No. 17 ("Upton Sinclair's 80th Birthday": leading article), Sep 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Wisdom of Mercy / Upton Sinclair (4 pp.), Jun 4, 1915; Fragile: Needs Conservation. Patrons must use photocopy only. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The World of Upton Sinclair" A Bibliography / Harry Laidler (2 pp.), [1958] (Box 1, Folder 9)